<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe dissection of Germaines affliction with warre, pestilence, and famine; and other deducable miseries, lachrimable to speak of; more lamentable to partake of. Sent as a (friendly) monitor to England, warning her to beware of, (generally) ingratitude, and security; as also (particularly) other greevous sinnes, the weight whereof Germany hath a long time felt, and at this present doth (and England may feare to) feele. Written from approv'd intelligence, by M. Parker.</title>
            <author>M. P. (Martin Parker), d. 1656?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119361</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854568</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854568</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19995</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08944)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19995)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1607:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe dissection of Germaines affliction with warre, pestilence, and famine; and other deducable miseries, lachrimable to speak of; more lamentable to partake of. Sent as a (friendly) monitor to England, warning her to beware of, (generally) ingratitude, and security; as also (particularly) other greevous sinnes, the weight whereof Germany hath a long time felt, and at this present doth (and England may feare to) feele. Written from approv'd intelligence, by M. Parker.</title>
                  <author>M. P. (Martin Parker), d. 1656?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T. Cotes for Francis Grove, dwelling on Snow- hill, neare the Sarazens head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures A B⁴ (-B4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Germany --  History --  1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19995:1"/>
            <p>A briefe diſſection OF <hi>Germaines</hi> Affliction: With Warre, Peſtilence, and Famine; and other deducable miſeries, Lachrimable to ſpeak of; more lamentable to partake of.</p>
            <p>Sent as a (friendly) monitor to <hi>England,</hi> warning her to beware of, <hi>(Generally)</hi> Ingratitude, and Security; as alſo <hi>(Particularly)</hi> Other greevous ſinnes, the weight whereof <hi>Germany</hi> hath a long time felt, and at this preſent doth (and <hi>England</hi> may feare to) feele.</p>
            <p>Written from approv'd intelligence, by <hi>M. Parker.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luk. 13.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Except yee repent, yee ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> London by <hi>T. Cotes,</hi> for <hi>Francis Grove,</hi> dwelling on Snow hill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neere the Sarazens head. 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19995:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19995:2"/>
            <head>To the tender hearted Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader ſhould this inſuing diſcourſe happen to be reade (or heard) by the moſt adamantine heart in the world; (I perſwade my ſelfe) it would (like Goats blood) diſſolve it. For here in this ſmall volume is briefly diſected (or ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomized) the largeſt ſubject of miſery that the lanthorne of time ever ſhewed to the world. It is a lamentable tragedy; ſo lamentable, that the like, all precedent times were ignorant of. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many is the Stage; the Actors are mercileſſe extortioners, bloody homicides, luxurious ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhers, ſacrilegious robbers, (and ſpoylers) of Churches and other holy places Canibalian man-eaters, and their attendants. And becauſe no play is held compleat unleſſe ſome womens parts be in it; behold here are Virgins raviſhed and murthered; women eating their owne children: nay, one woman devouring another. The Scenes are Warre, Famine, and Pestilence, with other
<pb facs="tcp:19995:3"/>
miſerable calamities deduced (or derived) from thence; the ſpectators or audience are men who have ſeene their houſes rob'd, their wives and daughters carnally abuſed in their owne ſight, their young ſucking babes daſhed against the walls by the heeles, or thruſt upon ſpeare points: Nay, ſome of them alſo eaten by barbarous Croats. Women likewiſe that have beheld their loving husbands, ſome miſerably tortured to death; others ſhamefully abuſed, and even gelt in their (enforced) preſence; others have had their noſes and eares cut off to make hat-bands for the deriding tormentors. Now loving Countrymen heare me, this hath long beene (and yet is) the caſe of afflicted Germany, that it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver may be our owne caſe, let us pitty hers, and leave off thoſe ſinnes which have drawne theſe plagues upon her, though we (by Gods mercy) are yet ſpared, that ſtill we may, and that our merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lord will continue his bleſsings, (health, peace and plenty) among us, is the daily prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Martin Parker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19995:3"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE DISECTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON OF <hi>GERMANIES</hi> AFFLICTION.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Paper (white before) hath reaſon juſt,</l>
               <l>In Sable weeds (theſe lines) it ſelfe to dreſſe,</l>
               <l>For what may here be read (if we may truſt</l>
               <l>Old Natures doctrine) ſhewes ſuch heavineſſe,</l>
               <l>That ſenceleſſe things may mourne, why ſhould no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>White Paper mourne, that beares black deeds of men</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Such ſtrange (unheard of) miſchiefes miſeries,</l>
               <l>Diſaſters, Murder, Sacriledge and Rape,</l>
               <l>That he who reads, (or heares) it with dry eyes;</l>
               <l>Shall paſſe o're what the Writer could not ſcape.</l>
               <l>Theſe are the Sceanes of this ſad Tragedy;</l>
               <l>Theſe make my Paper mourne, and ſo doe I;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:4"/>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Germany,</hi> Soveraigne of th' <hi>Europian</hi> part,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eate of the Sacred Chriſtian Empire, hath</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull twenty (late paſt) yeares, bin pearc'd toth'heart,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſtill deſtruction keepes his beaten path,</l>
               <l>Nor will be ſtopt, O that my prayers could ſtay</l>
               <l>His journey, I'd (and ſo will) ever pray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Millions of millions in theſe forenam'd yeares,</l>
               <l>On either part hath fallen by the ſword,</l>
               <l>By too well proov'd experience this appeares,</l>
               <l>Time in his brazen booke doth all record,</l>
               <l>O pitty 'tis that Chriſtians thus ſhould ſpill</l>
               <l>The blood of Chriſtians, but alas, they will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>We have a ſaying that's more true then old,</l>
               <l>He beſt knowes where the ſhooe wrings that does wear't</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o we who here injoy even what we would,</l>
               <l>And have no warre among's, nor doe we fear't.)</l>
               <l>Cannot diſcerne aright the direfull plight,</l>
               <l>Which th' Commons ſuffer under warres affright.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Let's with their leaſt of miſeries begin,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>magine now a man o're night with wealth</l>
               <l>Great ſtore, which toile, and care hath brought him in,</l>
               <l>And that his wife, and children all's in health,</l>
               <l>See him ere morne, behold the rape of's wife,</l>
               <l>And daughter firſt, then with his goods loſe life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:4"/>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>The cruell Souldiers void of all remorſe,</l>
               <l>Take ſhare of each mans labour at command,</l>
               <l>And whats deny'd or hid, they will by force</l>
               <l>Of horrid tortures purchaſe out of hand.</l>
               <l>The Commons (though in ſubſtance equilent)</l>
               <l>To be the Souldiers ſlaves muſt reſt content.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Reſt content ſaid I, theres two golden words,</l>
               <l>Which every man would happy be to finde</l>
               <l>True at his wiſh; but reſtleſſe warre affords,</l>
               <l>Reſt nor content to any, none in minde,</l>
               <l>Can be ſecure of what they doe poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>Where Souldiers can, they take all more and leſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>Yet don't miſtake me, I'me not generall</l>
               <l>In cenſuring of Souldiers; for I know,</l>
               <l>Some whoſe due praiſe for valour is not ſmall,</l>
               <l>Who in the martiall courſe will mercy ſhow.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Germany</hi> hath had (and ſtill retaines)</l>
               <l>An army whom the devill (their captaine) traines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10.</head>
               <l>Theſe are the Crabats (crabbed curres indeed)</l>
               <l>Vulgarly called Croats (barbarous ſlaves)</l>
               <l>Theſe like to <hi>Canibals</hi> on babes will feede,</l>
               <l>No quarter theyle allow to him that craves.</l>
               <l>I quake to ſet the deeds downe (with my pen)</l>
               <l>Done by theſe fiends of hell it he ſhape of men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:5"/>
               <head>11.</head>
               <l>Of other Nations (that have ſuch hard hearts)</l>
               <l>Great numbers be, yet all are <hi>Croats</hi> nam'd</l>
               <l>Becauſe in barbariſme they take their parts,</l>
               <l>By ſuch as theſe, true honour is defam'd,</l>
               <l>He who from <hi>Mars</hi> is borne Legitimate</l>
               <l>In loving honour, tyranny doth hate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>12.</head>
               <l>Theſe ſalvage (not true) Souldiers neither care</l>
               <l>For God, nor man, nor devill, where the gaine</l>
               <l>The conqueſt, neither age nor ſex they ſpare,</l>
               <l>To kneele, or begge, with teares to them's in vaine.</l>
               <l>The lives, of women, men, and infants ſweete,</l>
               <l>They weigh no more then wormes under their feet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>13.</head>
               <l>No Pagan, Turke, Tartarian, nor Iew,</l>
               <l>'Mongſt all their Tyrannies 'gainſt Chriſtians us'd,</l>
               <l>Such Stratagemes of villany ere knew,</l>
               <l>Both Male and Female they have ſo abus'd.</l>
               <l>'Tis terrible, and odious to unfold</l>
               <l>What hath (by them) beene done to young and old.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>14.</head>
               <l>Some have with match (or cord) ſo hard beene ty'd,</l>
               <l>That from eares, eyes, and noſe, the blood did ſpring</l>
               <l>From many of them (as tis teſtify'd)</l>
               <l>Their eyes have ſtarted out (O horrid ſinne)</l>
               <l>Some flead off skins alive, as Butchers will,</l>
               <l>Doe to thoſe Sheep, or Oxen which they kill,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:5"/>
               <head>15.</head>
               <l>Others with chiſels had their faces plaind,</l>
               <l>From th'fingers ends the blood from ſome did ſtart,</l>
               <l>To eate their excrements ſome were conſtraind,</l>
               <l>Thus every one did ſtrive to act his part,</l>
               <l>In cruelty, all others to excell,</l>
               <l>Thereby to gaine a place of note in hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>16.</head>
               <l>But one thing more is to be wonderd at</l>
               <l>Then all the reſt (O note this helliſh art,</l>
               <l>A Reverend Channon tortur'd with a cat,</l>
               <l>Fix'd to his naked belly ne're to ſtart,</l>
               <l>Till man and cat (through horrid paine and hunger)</l>
               <l>Yeelded to death, when they could live no longer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>17.</head>
               <l>Some had their privy parts, with powder fil'd,</l>
               <l>And blowne up intoth' ayre, have dyed ſo,</l>
               <l>Others by a more ſtrange device were kil'd</l>
               <l>Hangd up on high, a fire was made beloe,</l>
               <l>Of ſtuffe combuſtible, no flame but ſmoke,</l>
               <l>And with this policy they many choake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <head>18.</head>
               <l>Now Reader if tha'ſt read or heard whats told,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Diocleſian, Neroe, Phaleris,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doſt thinke they to theſe monſters might not hold</l>
               <l>The candle for invention; Surely yes,</l>
               <l>Theſe outſtrip them all, and that can be nam'd</l>
               <l>Although the world for Tyrants them proclaim'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:6"/>
               <head>19.</head>
               <l>For rape with Sacrilegious murder, and</l>
               <l>Robbing and ſpoyling Churches and the like,</l>
               <l>We from no ancient times can underſtand</l>
               <l>Such actions perpetrated that may ſtrike</l>
               <l>Men unto terror, and amazement both,</l>
               <l>To reade of that which I to write am loath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>20.</head>
               <l>Prieſts praying at the altars 'tis truth,</l>
               <l>Nuns raviſhed and with ſore tortures kild,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itch Burgers daughters in their blooming youth</l>
               <l>Have ſo beene ſerved, nay when their blood was ſpil'd</l>
               <l>And life departed, thoſe (who nought regard)</l>
               <l>Have carnally abus'd them afterward.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <head>21.</head>
               <l>One villaine having raviſhed a Mayd,</l>
               <l>Cut her alive in quarters with his ſword,</l>
               <l>While on his knees her aged Father prayd,</l>
               <l>To ſave her life, but got no other word</l>
               <l>To comfort him, but this, if thou wilt ſave her.</l>
               <l>Pray to the Saints, and try if they can ſave her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>22.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome Mayds and Wives (as ſad experience tels,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſave themſelves from ſordid villany</l>
               <l>Have headlong leaped into Lakes, and Wels,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbracing death to ſave their honeſty,</l>
               <l>Though verity condems ſuch deſperate facts</l>
               <l>Woe be to them who cauſe ſuch diſmall acts:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:6"/>
               <head>23.</head>
               <l>Women with childe, nay women in childbed,</l>
               <l>Theſe miſcreants, inſatiately have us'd</l>
               <l>Their husbands, and their friends they've tortured,</l>
               <l>Praying with teares to have their wives excus'd.</l>
               <l>O hatefull to be ſpoke, as bad to heare,</l>
               <l>What I could write manhood bids me forbeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <head>24.</head>
               <l>So much of that, too much ift pleas'd our Lord,</l>
               <l>Is't wonder if more plagues from this doe ſpring,</l>
               <l>Theſe miſchiefes all were brought in by the ſword,</l>
               <l>Now what ſucceeds all this, a worſer thing.</l>
               <l>Grim meager famine, through decay of tillage,</l>
               <l>Doth fiercely rage, in City, Towne, and village.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <head>25.</head>
               <l>Learned <hi>Joſephus</hi> in's Iudaicke warres</l>
               <l>Treating of proud <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> her ſiege;</l>
               <l>Writes that by famine more then by the ſcars</l>
               <l>O'th <hi>Romane</hi> ſwords, the draught of death did pledge</l>
               <l>That ſtory hath from me extracted teares</l>
               <l>And ſo may this from any he that heares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <head>26.</head>
               <l>If any difference be (in my conceite)</l>
               <l>It reſts in this which after ſhall inſue,</l>
               <l>Weighing each circumſtance this is more great,</l>
               <l>And might diſſolve the heart of any Iew</l>
               <l>A woman there I reade her childe did eate,</l>
               <l>Two women here did of their babes make meate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:7"/>
               <head>27.</head>
               <l>One was a Widdow i'th <hi>Palatinate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who had a daughter ſome nine yeares of age</l>
               <l>A Lamentable ſtory to relate,</l>
               <l>Hunger ſo furiouſly 'mongſt them did rage,</l>
               <l>They at contention fell one with another,</l>
               <l>Which ſhould be kild, the daughter or the mother.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <head>28.</head>
               <l>To render their ſad talke would be prolix,</l>
               <l>But thus (in briefe) the girle (with famine pind)</l>
               <l>Her gaſtly eyes did on her mother fix.</l>
               <l>Mother ſaid ſhee, I would you'd be ith mind</l>
               <l>To kill me, that my miſery might ceaſe.</l>
               <l>Or let me kill you, you of paine t'releaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <head>29.</head>
               <l>The woman looking wiſhly on the child,</l>
               <l>Sayes what wouldſt doe with me if I were dead,</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe Ide eate you, ſhe with hunger wild</l>
               <l>Vpon a ſudden caught the girle by'th head</l>
               <l>Puld off her hairelace; no long time ſhe wrangles,</l>
               <l>But with the ſame her daughter deere ſhee ſtrangles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
               <head>30.</head>
               <l>Wanting a knife, (O note what ſhift ſhe made)</l>
               <l>Famine in her maternall love exild)</l>
               <l>She cut the fleſh in gobets with a ſpade,</l>
               <l>Then dreſſing th'head and ſome part of the child.</l>
               <l>She fild her belly, and what did abound,</l>
               <l>Her neighbours bought (for porke) foure ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers the pound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:7"/>
               <head>31.</head>
               <l>Now what became of her when th'childe was miſt,</l>
               <l>How ſhe impriſon'd was arraign'd, and freed,</l>
               <l>There's no neceſſity to manifiſt,</l>
               <l>And to my ſelfe I have propoſed ſpeede,</l>
               <l>Therefore Ile end this tragicall diſcourſe,</l>
               <l>And tell another tale as bad or worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <head>32.</head>
               <l>At <hi>Hornebaſh</hi> a woman had a childe</l>
               <l>Of which ſhe had lyen inne not long before,</l>
               <l>Hunger that wilde things tames, makes tame things wilde,</l>
               <l>Oppreſt this woman and her babe ſo ſore,</l>
               <l>That ſhee foode lacking, milke it needs muſt want,</l>
               <l>And both for nutriment did feebly pant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
               <head>33.</head>
               <l>The woman ſeeing in what deepe diſtreſſe</l>
               <l>Her tender Infant was through want of food,</l>
               <l>And famine did her body ſo oppreſſe,</l>
               <l>That what to doe ſhe in amazement ſtood,</l>
               <l>Motherly pitty for the babe did plead,</l>
               <l>Neceſſity cries out it muſt be dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
               <head>34.</head>
               <l>Neceſſity prevailes, ſhe takes a knife,</l>
               <l>(My heart doth tremble while I write of it)</l>
               <l>Wherewith ſhe reſt the Innocent of life,</l>
               <l>And of the fleſh made many a ſavory bit.</l>
               <l>O famine there's no plague compares with thee,</l>
               <l>Thou art (by ods) the worſt of all the three.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:8"/>
               <head>35.</head>
               <l>This being knowne, ſhe was to'th Magiſtrates</l>
               <l>Brought and examined about her deede,</l>
               <l>To whom (in decent order) ſhe relates</l>
               <l>The motive; 'twas ſhe wanting foode to feede,</l>
               <l>Her ſelfe and it, to rid it out of paine,</l>
               <l>She murtherd it, her owne life to ſuſtaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36">
               <head>36.</head>
               <l>Quoth ſhe 'twas my owne fruite, and in that plight</l>
               <l>Ready to periſh both my ſelfe and it,</l>
               <l>I thought to uſe it, I had the moſt right,</l>
               <l>Yet Law (for all this) would not her aquit,</l>
               <l>She was condemn'd to dye (for examples ſake)</l>
               <l>Leaſt others to do the like ſhould undertake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37">
               <head>37.</head>
               <l>This wofull ſtory, which ſucceeds in place,</l>
               <l>Is full as Lamentable as wonderfull,</l>
               <l>Three Mayds that equall friendſhip did embrace</l>
               <l>Together dwelt, this famine did ſo pull,</l>
               <l>That mauger former love, which had beene ſhowne</l>
               <l>They ſought each others lives to ſave their owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
               <head>38.</head>
               <l>This to effect, two of them did conſpire,</l>
               <l>To kill (and eate) the third, (O pittious caſe)</l>
               <l>And quickly they accompliſht their deſire,</l>
               <l>Fierce hunger ſwiftly followed the chaſe,</l>
               <l>Betweene theſe two, the third in bed they kild,</l>
               <l>And with her fleſh their empty bellies fild.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="39">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:8"/>
               <head>39.</head>
               <l>When this was done and paſt, note the event,</l>
               <l>Hearts once obdur'd and hands inur'd to ill,</l>
               <l>Once fleſh'd in miſchiefe; ſoone the minds aſſent,</l>
               <l>Is wonne to any thing be't what it will.</l>
               <l>So hapn'd it with theſe two, the third was ſlaine,</l>
               <l>Want wrought conſpiracy betweene thoſe twaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
               <head>40.</head>
               <l>One ſtrangled the other in her bed,</l>
               <l>(Thus miſchiefe multipli'd, no love, no feare)</l>
               <l>And as they ſerv'd the firſt (cut off her head)</l>
               <l>This ſhe alone perform'd to her compeere,</l>
               <l>And having eaten't, ſhe proceeded further,</l>
               <l>Her heart was hard, ſhe made no bones of murther.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="41">
               <head>41.</head>
               <l>She goes one day unto a village neare,</l>
               <l>A friend to viſit (as ſhe did pretend)</l>
               <l>Whoſe husband was from home; ſhe lov'd her deare,</l>
               <l>And bad her welcome, (like a loving friend)</l>
               <l>But in the night (lying with her in bed)</l>
               <l>This murtherous mayd cut off the womans head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42">
               <head>42.</head>
               <l>And binding the dead body on a board,</l>
               <l>Brought it toth' place where ſhe did dwell.</l>
               <l>Fierce famine would not ſo much time afford,</l>
               <l>To let her cut it out (like joynts to ſell)</l>
               <l>She took both hands and head, which waſhing clean</l>
               <l>When they were boyl'd to eate them ſhe did mean.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="43">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:9"/>
               <head>43.</head>
               <l>The good man comming home his wife did mis,</l>
               <l>And for her 'mongſt his neighbors did demand,</l>
               <l>Who could give no intelligence but this,</l>
               <l>That ſuch a Mayd was with her: out of hand</l>
               <l>To her he trudges, askes if ſhe did kno</l>
               <l>What was become of's wife? ſhe anſwer'd no.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44">
               <head>44.</head>
               <l>But ſuch things can't be hid, murther will out,</l>
               <l>A guilty looke betrayes a guilty heart,</l>
               <l>He goes into the houſe and all about</l>
               <l>He pryeth (narrowly) in every part,</l>
               <l>And in this Inquiſition 'twas his lot</l>
               <l>To ſpy one of the hands ſticke out o'th pot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="45">
               <head>45.</head>
               <l>Then being (no marvell) in impetuous rage,</l>
               <l>He threatens her, who ſoone the fact confeſt,</l>
               <l>Saying, it was harſh hunger to aſſwage,</l>
               <l>Made her doe that and more, then told the reſt,</l>
               <l>And ſtraight to <hi>Stiltzy</hi> (by three Musketeers)</l>
               <l>She was conveyed before th'imperiall Peers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="46">
               <head>46.</head>
               <l>While ſhe before the Iudgement ſeat did ſtand</l>
               <l>To be arraign'd, according to the Law,</l>
               <l>The Sodden hand ſhe held within her hand,</l>
               <l>And that all other might be kept in aw.</l>
               <l>Her head was cut off with a ſword of ſteele,</l>
               <l>Her body was faſt bound unto a wheele.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="47">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:9"/>
               <head>47.</head>
               <l>There for a ſpectacle ſtill to remaine</l>
               <l>That all may ſhun murther (that crying crime)</l>
               <l>Although neceſſity did her conſtraine,</l>
               <l>She taſting the affliction of the time,</l>
               <l>Yet having dipp'd her hands in blood ſo often,</l>
               <l>Twas fit that death her flinty heart ſhould ſoften.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="48">
               <head>48.</head>
               <l>A woman in the village of <hi>Steinhauſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A girle of twelve yeares, and a boy of five,</l>
               <l>Did kill and eate for which inhumane cauſe,</l>
               <l>(Being found) the Law did her of life deprive,</l>
               <l>And at her execution ſhe told plaine,</l>
               <l>That ſhe laſt yeare kild other children twaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="49">
               <head>49.</head>
               <l>I'th Pariſh of <hi>Swegbruggen</hi> there a brother,</l>
               <l>And ſiſter did ſurvive their Paren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s dead,</l>
               <l>The ſiſter dies, he eates her and of's mother,</l>
               <l>Devours the thighes, Oh horrible to reade,</l>
               <l>A woefull ſpectacle to them who ſee't,</l>
               <l>Where ſtarved people fall downe dead ith ſtreet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="50">
               <head>50.</head>
               <l>And of the dead, the living make their meate,</l>
               <l>Out of their bellies, they the intrailes pull</l>
               <l>Hearts, Livers, Lungs, o'th dead the living eate</l>
               <l>(A ſtory true woefull, and wonderfull)</l>
               <l>Snayles, Frogs, and Carrion, dead ſixe weeks before</l>
               <l>To this diſtreſſe, what can be added more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="51">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:10"/>
               <head>51.</head>
               <l>A woman in the ſtreetes that was found dead,</l>
               <l>Betweene her teeth a humane rib did hold,</l>
               <l>And hard by her lay roaſted a mans head</l>
               <l>A wonderous tragicke tale tis to be told;</l>
               <l>Children cry in the ſtreetes and dare not goe</l>
               <l>Home, fearing killing, hunger rageth ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="52">
               <head>52.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome eating mad dogs have themſelves runne mad,</l>
               <l>And raging dy'd in Lamentable plight,</l>
               <l>A miniſters wife that ſix ſweete children had</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw them all ſtarv'd to death in her owne ſight,</l>
               <l>So many wanting food to taſte, have taſted</l>
               <l>Of death, that all th' <hi>Palatinates</hi> devaſted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="53">
               <head>53.</head>
               <l>The Countries turn'd into a wilderneſſe</l>
               <l>For in three hundred Pariſhes (O ſtrange)</l>
               <l>Not one is left alive ſuch deepe diſtreſſe</l>
               <l>That Country feeles; an admirable change;</l>
               <l>Twas once the Eden of all Chriſtendome,</l>
               <l>Yet now to utter ruine it is come.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="54">
               <head>54.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the whole Dukedome of <hi>Swegbruggen</hi> are</l>
               <l>A live two hundred ninety two, no more</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n all that ſpacious Province death did ſpare</l>
               <l>But theſe (to mourne for them that went before)</l>
               <l>A wonderous ſtory tis alas (too true)</l>
               <l>Of milions left two hundred ninety two.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="55">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:10"/>
               <head>55.</head>
               <l>So furiouſly this monſter (Famin) raves,</l>
               <l>(That tis no marvell if they eate it freſh)</l>
               <l>That people dig'd dead bodies out of graves,</l>
               <l>And to ſuſtaine their lives have eate the fleſh,</l>
               <l>This is a miſery, myſtery't may be ſed,</l>
               <l>When by the dead the living muſt be fed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="56">
               <head>56.</head>
               <l>At <hi>Wormes,</hi> and divers other places, want</l>
               <l>Doth tyranniz ſo o're the common ſort,</l>
               <l>That in high wayes and ſtreets they lye and pant,</l>
               <l>What ſhifts they make tis wondrous to report.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Saxony</hi> and alſo on the <hi>Rhine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This Plague of Plagues doth many people pine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="57">
               <head>57.</head>
               <l>Horſe fleſh is common, that I count good meat,</l>
               <l>(Taking the place and ſeaſon as it haps)</l>
               <l>But here they (vermin) Rats, and Mice doe eate,</l>
               <l>For which with diligence, they ſet their traps:</l>
               <l>Nay dogs and cats, are at the market ſold,</l>
               <l>And glad is he that firſt of it layes hold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="58">
               <head>58.</head>
               <l>A Buſhell of corne (with difficulty brought)</l>
               <l>Eighteene Rix dollers, there will eaſly yeeld</l>
               <l>And glad are they by whom the ſame is bought,</l>
               <l>Tis food (not money) that is hungers ſhield,</l>
               <l>It is in Engliſh coyne, foure pounds, twelve pence</l>
               <l>To ſave their Lives they will not ſpare expence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="59">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:11"/>
               <head>59.</head>
               <l>Our meaner ſort in <hi>England</hi> are ſo nice,</l>
               <l>(Vnleſſe by chance there be ſome dearth of corne)</l>
               <l>I have obſerv'd it more then once or twice</l>
               <l>How in the markets, they Rye meale will ſcorne,</l>
               <l>And other things, which I muſt overſlip,</l>
               <l>For feare ſome Scold ſhould take me on the hip.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="60">
               <head>60.</head>
               <l>But take heed <hi>England,</hi> leaſt when th'art full fed</l>
               <l>Thou doe forget thy God (I doubt thou doſt)</l>
               <l>While thou haſt foule and fiſh with fill of bread,</l>
               <l>Thinke on poore <hi>Germany</hi> who once could boſt</l>
               <l>Of plenty more then all the Chriſtian world,</l>
               <l>Yet ſee into what miſery ſhees hurld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="61">
               <head>61.</head>
               <l>Tis now her caſe why may not thine be next,</l>
               <l>Thy ſins are equall if not more then hers,</l>
               <l>And ſith our Lord, at every ſinner's vext,</l>
               <l>What is the reaſon that he thee prefers,</l>
               <l>And her dejects, be humble leaſt thou feele</l>
               <l>What ſhe hath felt, thinke on <hi>Sapora's</hi> wheele.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="62">
               <head>62.</head>
               <l>Heaven gently hath ſcourgd thee not long ſince,</l>
               <l>With a ſmall Plague to make thee feare a biger,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Germany</hi> hath had ſuch peſtilence,</l>
               <l>That it appeares the viols of his riger</l>
               <l>Are powr'd on her, O miſerable ſtate,</l>
               <l>Woe is me if thee I don't compaſſionate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="63">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:11"/>
               <head>63</head>
               <l>In <hi>Switzerland</hi> the City <hi>Baſſile</hi> there,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Anno</hi> ſixteene hundred thirty three,</l>
               <l>Bury'd full twenty thouſand in that yeare,</l>
               <l>Of the ſwift peſtilence which none can flee;</l>
               <l>And in the next yeare following, that in <hi>Trent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Full thirty thouſand the ſame journey went.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="64">
               <head>64.</head>
               <l>And divers parts in <hi>Belgia</hi> are diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>With this contagion whoſe expanſion wide,</l>
               <l>Claimes Soveraignty (though an unwelcome gueſt)</l>
               <l>He'l lodge with wives even by their husbands ſide,</l>
               <l>Where ere he comes, he either all doth take,</l>
               <l>Or elſe diviſion among friends he'l make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="65">
               <head>65.</head>
               <l>This foule infection did ſo overſpread,</l>
               <l>All <hi>Germany</hi> that ſcarce a place was free,</l>
               <l>Potentates from their uſuall places fled,</l>
               <l>Yet ſafe in any part they could not be.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nimegen, Guelders, Emericke</hi> and the <hi>Hague,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and <hi>Bruxels,</hi> all have had this Plague.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="66">
               <head>66.</head>
               <l>In <hi>Bavier</hi> ſo many people fell,</l>
               <l>The living could not bury all the dead,</l>
               <l>But Rats, and Mice, (a miſery tis to tell)</l>
               <l>Familiarly upon the bodyes fed.</l>
               <l>A lamentable ſpectacle to ſee,</l>
               <l>Chiefly for they who tender hearted be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="67">
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:12"/>
               <head>67.</head>
               <l>And unto ſuch I dedicate my labours.</l>
               <l>(As in th'Epiſtle they may reade who pleaſe)</l>
               <l>Who with compaſſion thinke upon their Neighbours,</l>
               <l>And in their mindes doe ſeeke Gods wrath t'appeaſe,</l>
               <l>For Charity, and Verity, doth call</l>
               <l>Vpon us, that we ſhould doe good to all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="68">
               <head>68.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f we doe not lament with them that mourne</l>
               <l>And weepe with them that ſorrow, iſt not juſt,</l>
               <l>That if't (as God forbid) ſhould be our turne</l>
               <l>To have our glory bury'd in the duſt,)</l>
               <l>That others ſhould not pitty our eſtate,</l>
               <l>How can we love God, and our brother hate.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:19995:12"/>
            <head>The Epilogue or Poſtſcript to the Reader.</head>
            <l>THus (tender hearted Reader have I ſet</l>
            <l>Before thine eyes (what thou ſhouldſt nere forget)</l>
            <l>The miſery which neighbour Nations feele,</l>
            <l>Through war, famine, and peſtilence, the wheele</l>
            <l>Of Fortune's ſtill in motion, though we ſit</l>
            <l>In peace, and plenty, yet ith midſt of it,</l>
            <l>Tis fit we ſhould on <hi>Ioſephs</hi> troubles thinke,</l>
            <l>Leaſt of the cup of wrath, we alſo drinke,</l>
            <l>Let's all conſider tis th' Almighties hand,</l>
            <l>That ſtriketh others, and doth ſpare our land,</l>
            <l>And that his love, (not our deſarts) are cauſe,</l>
            <l>Why from our Nation he the ſtroke withdrawes,</l>
            <l>We are as wicked (if not more) then they</l>
            <l>On whom he doth his rod of anger lay,</l>
            <l>And therefore though as yet we live in mirth,</l>
            <l>(Injoying all the bleſsings upon earth,</l>
            <l>A Gracious King, under whoſe Governement</l>
            <l>We live, in peace, and for our more content</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19995:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Are fortifi'd with Royall Off-ſpring which</l>
            <l>Our land with future bleſsings may inrich,)</l>
            <l>Yet if this peace and plenty which we have,</l>
            <l>Doe make us proud, forgetting him who gave</l>
            <l>Vs all theſe comforts, which our neighbours want,</l>
            <l>We well may feare, leaſt he his love tranſplant,</l>
            <l>Into another people, that will yeild</l>
            <l>A larger crop of thankes; O let the field</l>
            <l>Of each ones heart, receive the ſeede of grace,</l>
            <l>And with true gratitude prevent his face,</l>
            <l>Lets hate our loved ſins, our vaine exceſſe</l>
            <l>Of (Luciferian) pride, ſloth, drunkenneſſe,</l>
            <l>Extortion, avarice, and luxury,</l>
            <l>Let's feede and cloath Christ in neceſsity,</l>
            <l>I meane in's little ones, what's done to them,</l>
            <l>His owne words ratifie, as done to him,</l>
            <l>This is his will, to do't lets all endever,</l>
            <l>And he (no doubt) will give us peace for ever.</l>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19995:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
